<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on Wild Econometrics &amp; R</title>
    <link>s3alfisc.github.io/blog/categories/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on Wild Econometrics &amp; R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="s3alfisc.github.io/blog/categories/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Testing an R package against a Julia package on github actions</title>
      <link>s3alfisc.github.io/blog/post/testing-an-r-package-against-a-julia-package-via-github-actions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>s3alfisc.github.io/blog/post/testing-an-r-package-against-a-julia-package-via-github-actions/</guid>
      <description>Something I have learned the hard way: every single line of code that I write should be accompanied by a unit test. Unit tests are not only useful for me as a developer to spot bugs, but a thorough sequence of unit tests should also increase others’ confidence in the quality of my code.
For statistical methods and algorithms, one great way to test if everything is working as intended is to test one’s own implementation of an algorithm against someone else’s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1000x faster Wild Cluster Bootstrap Inference in R with fwildclusterboot</title>
      <link>s3alfisc.github.io/blog/post/1000x-faster-wild-cluster-bootstrap-inference-in-r-with-fwildclusterboot/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>s3alfisc.github.io/blog/post/1000x-faster-wild-cluster-bootstrap-inference-in-r-with-fwildclusterboot/</guid>
      <description>When you suspect that the error terms in your regression model are correlated within clusters, and the number of clusters is small, trouble might be running at you. In such a situation, common cluster robust standard errors tend to be downward biased - they are too eager to reject the null hypothesis. Since Cameron, Gelbach &amp;amp; Miller first suggested that the wild cluster bootstrap might be preferable to sandwich standard errors when the number of clusters is small, it has become common practice among empirical economists to check their cluster robust inferences against the wild cluster bootstrap.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
